<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../src-generated/schemas/fhir-single.xsd">
  <a name="introduction"> </a>
  <h3>Introduction</h3>
  <p>To better illustrate the Outcome Criteria Framework, this guide includes a comprehensive Depression Outcomes example, as illustrated by the following Figure. Sections that follow describe the components of this example.</p>
  <p>The heart of this example is the depressionOutcomes CQL library file which is contained by reference in the depressionOutcomes FHIR Library resource. Definitions in this CQL library file are used by the depression measure quality measure and by the depression intervention event-condition-action rule in the FHIR PlanDefinition resource. </p>
  <p>
    Given the central importance of the depressionOutcomes CQL library file in this example, we also provide 'pseudologic' for the formal definitions in the CQL file, which can be found <a href="depressionPseudologic.html">here</a>. </p>
  <img src="DepressionExample.png" alt="DepressionExample"/>

  <a name="exampleFiles"> </a>
  <h3>Example Files</h3>
  <ul>
    <li><b>FHIR Library: depressionOutcomes:</b> Contains a CQL library that encodes depression outcome criteria as defined by the AHRQ expert panel.</li>
    <li><b>CQL Library: depressionOutcomes:</b> Encodes depression outcome criteria as defined by the AHRQ expert panel.      Given the central importance of the depressionOutcomes CQL library file in this example, we also provide 'pseudologic' for the formal definitions in the CQL file, which can be found <a href="depressionPseudologic.html">here</a>.</li>
    <li><b>FHIR Measure: depression measure:</b> Defines a depression quality measure.</li>
    <li><b>FHIR Library: depressionMeasure:</b> Contains a CQL library that encodes measure-specific criteria (such as Denominator criteria).</li>
    <li><b>CQL Library: depressionMeasure:</b> Encodes measure-specific criteria (such as Denominator criteria).</li>
    <li><b>FHIR PlanDefinition: depression intervention:</b> Defines a depression 'event-condition-action' rule.</li>
    <li><b>FHIR Library: depressionIntervention:</b> Contains a CQL library that encodes decision support criteria (such as Trigger criteria).</li>
    <li><b>CQL Library: depressionIntervention:</b> Encodes decision support criteria (such as Trigger criteria).</li>
  </ul>

</div>
