<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../src-generated/schemas/fhir-single.xsd">
  <a name="overview"> </a>
  <h3>Introduction</h3>
  <p>
    The Outcome Criteria Framework is illustrated by the following Figure. Sections that follow describe both normative and non-normative aspects of the Framework.
  </p>
  <img src="overview.png" alt="Overview of what we're doing"/>

  <a name="NORMorg"> </a>
  <h3>Normative organization framework</h3>
  <p>
    The following are normative constraints per this guide:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>FHIR resources reference 0..* FHIR Library</li>
    <li>No FHIR resource other than the FHIR Library resource makes a direct CQL reference. </li>
    <li>Asserted expressions within a FHIR resource are contained in CQL library referenced by FHIR Library</li>
    <li>FHIR Library references 1..1 CQL library</li>
    <li>Each CQL library is wrapped in a FHIR Library</li>
    <li>A CQL library is a stand-alone file, not encoded within a FHIR Library</li>
    <li>Deliberate redundancy is defined for select fields in FHIR Library and CQL library, as shown in the following table - former is for library management whereas latter is for code execution.</li>
  </ul>
  <table>
    <tr><th>FHIR Library</th><th>CQL library</th></tr>
    <tr><td>dataRequirement</td><td>using (e.g. using FHIR version '4.0.1)</td></tr>
    <tr><td>relatedArtifact (depends-on)</td><td>include (e.g. include FHIRHelpers version '4.0.1')</td></tr>
    <tr><td>dataRequirement</td><td>valueset (e.g. valueset "Depression Condition": 'http://ct...)</td></tr>  
  </table>
  
  <a name="NORMsemantic"> </a>
  <h3>Normative semantic framework</h3>
  <p>
    The following are normative constraints per this guide:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>FHIR Library uses standardized metadata</li>
    <li>CQL must address all attributes where isModifier=true</li>
    <li>CQL must adhere to the following constraints, taken from the <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/cqfmeasures/using-cql.html">Quality Measure IG</a>
	   <ul>
	      <li><a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/cqfmeasures/using-cql.html#conformance-requirement-18">Conformance Requirement 18 (Library Declaration)</a></li>
	      <li><a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/cqfmeasures/using-cql.html#conformance-requirement-19">Conformance Requirement 19 (Library Versioning)</a></li>
	      <li><a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/cqfmeasures/using-cql.html#conformance-requirement-23">Conformance Requirement 23 (Code System Specification)</a></li>
	      <li><a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/cqfmeasures/using-cql.html#conformance-requirement-24">Conformance Requirement 24 (Value Set Specification)</a></li>
	   </ul>
	</li>
    <li>eCQM: Use FHIR Measure resource</li>
    <li>CDS: Use FHIR PlanDefinition; FHIR ActivityDefinition resources</li>
    <li>Research: Use FHIR ResearchDefinition; FHIR ResearchElementDefinition resources</li>
    <li>QI Core used as data model where possible. Else, use US Core.</li>
  </ul>

  <a name="NonNORM"> </a>
  <h3>Non-normative guidance</h3>
  <p>
    Non-normative guidance is focused on considerations that maximize reusability. The considerations are non-normative because exceptions exist, insufficient use cases have been analyzed, and because the rules are more fuzzy and therefore less amenable to computational validation. </p>
  <h4>Considerations for maximizing reusability</h4>	
  <ul>
    <li><b>Timing</b>: We want to enable users to have the option to either select their own measure intervals or use canned intervals that are baked into core definitions. Therefore, our general approach will be to create both time-neutral (e.g. 'All-cause mortality') and time-specified (e.g. '12 month all-cause mortality') definitions. </li>
    <li><b>Status</b>: We want to enable users to have some flexibility in cohorts with respect to condition status. Therefore, our general approach will be to NOT include condition status constraints in core definitions unless clearly required. For instance, the definition of 'Depression' does not include a constraint that Depression be active, since there may be cases where a group wants to study events that occur amongst patients whose depression is in remission.</li>
    <li><b>Condition-neutral criteria</b>: all cause mortality - base definition doesn't even include depression, so that it reusable to other conditions. </li>
  </ul>

</div>
